<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitallatin.github.io/guidelines/critical-editions.rng"
            type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitallatin.github.io/guidelines/critical-editions.rng"
            type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Decretum Gratiani</title>
        <author>Gratian, active 12th century</author>
        <editor>Paul Evans</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Stephan Kuttner Institute</publisher>
        <date>2020</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front xml:id="front">
      <div type="section" xml:id="preface">
        <head>Preface</head>
        <p>The text of the rubrics for 4.6.1 and 4.6.2 is quite similar in all
        four R1 mss., and substantially different from the readings reported in
        Fr. 4.6.1: "Qui in accusatione episcopi culpabilis inuenitur ad
        arguendum de cetero non admittatur nisi propriam causam ciuilem
        solummodo asserere uoluerit" in Aa Bc Fd P, and "In ciuili et proprio
        dumtaxat negotio ad arguendum admittitur, qui in episcopi accusatione
        culpabilis inuenitur" in Fr. 4.6.2: "Non negatur audientia in propria
        causa cuius accusatio interdicitur" in Aa Bc Fd P, and "Propriam causam
        agere ualet cui accusare non licet" in Fr.</p>
        <p>C.4 q.2-3 d.p.c.3 quotes a cryptic statement, not found in Clavis
        Canonum, attributed to St. Brice (†.444), a controversial disciple of
        St. Martin, and his successor as bishop of Tours.</p>
        <p>The most interesting text in the case is Gratian's one and
        only dictum, C.4 q.2-3 d.p.c.3. "Set obicitur illud beati
        Bricii, qui uoce pueri xxx dies ab ortu habentis innocens
        probatus est. Set miracula diuina sunt admiranda, non in
        exemplum humane actionis trahenda." The Latin of the first
        sentence is somewhat opaque. Taking the accusative plural
        dies as the object of habentis, and supplying exemplum
        because it is neuter and can be construed with illud, the
        sentence can be literally translated as "But that [example]
        of blessed Brice is objected, who was proved innocent by
        the voice of the child having thirty days from its birth
        or origin." The dictum can be translated into more idiomatic
        English as "But a counter-example is that of St. Brice, who
        was proved innocent by the word of a thirty-day-old child.
        But divine miracles are to be wondered at, not to be taken
        as a pattern for human action."</p>
        <p>Gratian is referring to a story from Gregory of Tours,
        History of the Franks, II.1, about St. Brice (†.444), St.
        Martin's controversial immediate successor as bishop of
        Tours. This is the only mention of Brice in the Decretum,
        and History of the Franks falls outside what we normally
        consider to be the boundaries of Gratian's formal or material
        sources. (Friedberg attributes the story to the Life of St.
        Martin by Sulpicius Severus, although he really seems to
        have had in mind an unrelated story from the third book of
        Sulpicius's Dialogues in which Marin compares Brice to
        Judas. In any event Friedberg was wrong, the proper attribution
        is to Gregory.) Gregory relates the story of a nun or
        consecrated virgin serving as a laundress for Brice's
        episcopal household who became pregnant and delivered a
        child. The people of Tours, with whom Brice was already
        quite unpopular, suspected that he was the father. Brice
        had the thirty-day-old infant brought to him, and questioned
        the child publicly concerning his paternity. Through the
        saint's miraculous intervention, the child spoke plainly,
        answering that Brice was not its father.</p>
        <p>The dictum is relevant in its immediate context, since
        Gratian is concluding his treatment of the second question,
        whether someone under the age of fourteen is able to testify
        in a criminal case. But Gratian's reference to this obscure
        story also seems intended to caution against depending on
        miracles as a regular part of criminal procedure, and by
        extension implies a negative judgement on the validity of
        trial by ordeal.</p>
        <p><note place="foot">"It is remarkable that in his dicta
        Gratian refers to sources that are not cited in the Decretum.
        Many biblical citations, for example, are found only in the
        dicta. They are often tied to important theological reflections
        ..." (Landau, "Gratian and the Decretum Gratiani", 41.)</note></p>
        <!-- Admont (Aa) -->
        <p>There are two marginal glosses in the Aa text of C.4 that refer to
        Burchard's <title level="m">Decretum</title>: "B.xvi. Nemo ſimul ſit."
        (Burchard 16.15) at 4.4.1, and "B.i. Qͥſqͥs." (Burchard 1.160) at 4.6.1.
        A rubric in between C.4 and C.5 ("Explicit liber quintus, incipit liber
        sextus, de episcoporum accusationibus") indicates a non-standard
        division of Aa into books.</p>
        <!-- Barcelona (Bc) -->
        <p>The order of rubrics in C.4 q.4 is reversed in Bc. The rubric for
        4.4.2 ("Quilibet in causa duas personas gerere non valet") appears
        before 4.4.1, and the rubric for 4.4.1 ("Accusator, testis vel iudex
        aliquis simul esse non potest") appears before 4.4.2. Bc includes two
        canons —  4.6.3 and 4.6.4 — not listed in Winroth's appendix and not
        found in either Aa or P.</p>
        <!-- Paris (P) -->
        <p>The quality of scribal workmanship in P is visibly less professional
        than that in either Aa or Bc.</p>
        <!-- cf. Mantello and Rigg -->
        <p>In addition to scribal errors, Aa, Bc, and P reflect divergence from
        Classical Latin orthography for
        <hi rend="italic">ci</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ti</hi>. Aa: spacium;
        Bc: defitiens, iuditio and iuditium, and prouintie; and P: accionis,
        audiencia, and tercio.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <!-- translation by Stanley Chodorow, 2 March 2019 -->
      <div type="translation" xml:id="translation-text" xml:space="preserve">
        <head>Translation</head>
        <div subtype="part" type="section">
          <div type="section" subtype="case" n="C.4">
            <head>(C.4)</head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="dictum" n="C.4 d.init.">
              <head>(C.4 d.init.)</head>
              <ab>
                An excommunicate undertook to accuse a bishop. He brought a
                person under the age of 14 to support his case. [assertio was
                originally used to mean the defense of a person’s character. In
                the middle ages the word took on a modern meaning of assertion.
                It retained its positive meaning—i.e. it was a statement in favor
                of something. Here, I think it means that the accuser brought the
                young person in to support his accusation against the bishop.]
                Prohibited from making the accusation [because he was an
                excommunicate], he made [introduced, assigned] the adolescent the
                accuser and himself the witness. [In other words, the
                excommunicate switched roles with the youth, but the next sentence
                raises a question about the meaning of se here.] The adolescent
                began to act as accuser and witness. On the appointed day, the
                bishop did not agree [minime concurrit] to come before the
                electors’ [those chosen to be judges] court. He was suspended from
                communion. Finally, the court having been reconvened, the accuser
                [I believe this refers to the youth] was found culpable in making
                the accusation. In the end, he [I believe this person is the
                original accuser, the excommunicate] proceeded to make his case.
              </ab>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back></back>
  </text>
</TEI>
